Disputes belong to civil law, which means that the parties in a dispute can only be private individuals, companies or associations.
There are two different types of disputes.
Dispositive and indispositive.
In indispositive disputes, there are only two possible outcomes.
It cannot be reconciled in such disputes.
A good example is a dispute over paternity where there are only two possible outcomes.
Dispositive disputes, on the other hand, are disputes where it is possible to compromise and negotiate.
Common such disputes are divorces, conflicts regarding contract interpretation, custody of children or money.
The rest of this video will be about dispositive disputes.
Dispositive disputes can be resolved both in or outside the court.
It is very good to agree with a lawyer with his counterparty outside the court with the help of a lawyer.
Then the counterparties can advantageously establish a settlement agreement that regulates how the solution becomes.
The dispute goes to court if one of the parties submits a lawsuit against the other party.
The party that submits the lawsuit is called a plaintiff.
A lawsuit is a document where the plaintiff describes his views on the situation and, through so -called claims, demands what the counterparty should do.
Once the court has received the lawsuit, the court will ask the counterparty to respond to the requirements of a so -called defense.
In this case, the counterparty is called defendant, as it must respond to the requirements.
After this exchange of letters, both parties meet on the so -called oral preparation.
In the presence of a judge, the two parties negotiate and try to agree on a compromise.
Such a compromise is called a settlement.
If it becomes a settlement, the court signs a settlement agreement that both signs and which tells what each party should do.
If the parties do not agree in a settlement, the case goes on to a main hearing.
In the main hearing, both parties report on their views on the situation.
Then the judge makes a decision on how the case should be resolved.
The party that loses may replace the winning party according to what is in the judgment.
The loser also bears responsibility for the winning party's legal costs for legal representatives, lost work income and other costs.
If there is no clear winner in the case, the costs will be allocated in proportion to the distribution in the judgment.
Often, your home insurance covers large parts of the costs.
Contact a lawyer and your insurance company for an individual assessment.
How should you do if you have ended up in a dispute
What you can do if you want to sue someone or if you yourself have been sued is to gather all the evidence that can prove your cause.
Collect any sms, email conversations, letters, agreements or other.
In addition, you can contact people who may have witnessed the situation or agreement.
Another advice is that it is good if you are objective to the situation and try to keep the emotions in control.
It can help you get a compromise with your counterpart and save you a lot of time and money.
One last advice is that you contact a lawyer who can help you with your case and can best assess the situation and how you can maximize your chances of success.
Thanks for watching
Feel free to press the like button if the video was useful.